MATTEO PEZZULLA EPFL

Lausanne, CH

@ matteo.pezzulla@epfl.ch \$\(\pi\) +41 76 437 19 25 * mpezzulla.com Skype ID: matteo.pezzulla

Date of Birth: August 3, 1988

CITIZENSHIP: Italian

Summary of qualifications & assets

I am a Postdoctoral Associate in the flexLab at EPFL.

My current research involves aspects of fluid-structure interactions relevant to the understanding of the behavior of porous wings at low Reynolds numbers. I also keep an interest on the theoretical and applied mechanics of thin shells. I work among solid mechanics, fluid mechanics, and differential geometry and I am interested in analytical, numerical, and experimental methods.

I am a member of the Italian Research Group in Mathematical Physics (GNFM) and the American Physical Society (APS).

EXPERIENCE

Nov 2017 – currently Postdoctoral Associate at École Polytechnique Fédérale de Lausanne

Supervisor: Prof. Pedro M. Reis

Nov 2015 – Oct 2017 Postdoctoral Associate at Boston University

Supervisor: Prof. Douglas P. Holmes

EDUCATION

FEBRUARY 2016 Ph.D. in THEORETICAL AND APPLIED MECHANICS,

Sapienza - Università di Roma

with honors

Focus: Morphing of Thin Soft Structures Driven by Geometry and Swelling

Advisor: Prof. Paola NARDINOCCHI

Aug – Dec 2014 Visiting Scholar at Boston University

Advisor: Prof. Douglas P. Holmes

October 2012 M.Sc. in Space Engineering, Sapienza - Università di Roma

110/110 cum laude

Thesis: "On the control of the large deformations occurring in IPMCs"

Advisor: Prof. Paola NARDINOCCHI

October 2010 B.Sc. in Aerospace Engineering, Sapienza - Università di Roma

110/110 cum laude

Thesis: "Bending deformations in ionic polymer metal composites induced by

mechano-electro-chemical interactions"

Advisor: Prof. Paola NARDINOCCHI

Talks, Presentations & Posters

- M. Pezzulla, P. Leroy-Catalayud, F. Gallaire, and P. M. Reis. "Fluid-Structure Interactions in Bristled Insect Wings" at APS/DFD 2019, Seattle, USA, November, 23–26.
- M. Pezzulla, F. Gallaire, and P. M. Reis. "Fluid-Structure Interactions in Bristled Insect Wings" at Fluids and Elasticity 2019, Malaga, Spain, June, 24–26.
- M. Pezzulla, L. Siconolfi, F. Gallaire, and P. M. Reis. "To Leak or not to Leak through Holey Sheets" at APS/DFD 2018, Atlanta, USA, November, 18–20.
- M. Pezzulla, E. Strong, H. Karimi, and P. M. Reis. "Deformation of perforated elastic sheets due to the hydrodynamic loading by a viscous fluid" at ESMC 2018, Bologna, Italy, July, 2–6.
- M. Pezzulla, E. Strong, H. Karimi, and P. M. Reis. "Deformation of perforated elastic sheets due to the hydrodynamic loading by a viscous fluid" at APS March Meeting 2018, Los Angeles, California, USA, March, 5–9.
- D. Yan, A. Lee, M. Pezzulla, F. Lopez Jimenez, J. Marthelot, D. P. Holmes, and P. M. Reis. "For Better or For Worse: Self-tuning of the buckling strength of active bilayer shells" at APS March Meeting 2018, Los Angeles, California, USA, March, 5–9.
- M. Pezzulla, N. Stoop, M. Steranka, A. Bade, M. Trejo, and D. P. Holmes. "Global Curvature Buckling and Snapping of Spherical Shells" at APS March Meeting 2017, New Orleans, Louisiana, USA, March, 13–17.
- M. Pezzulla and D. P. Holmes. "Geometry and Instabilities in Growing Shells" at NEW.Mech 2016, Harvard University, USA, October, 22.
- 2016 M. Pezzulla and D. P. Holmes. "Morphing and Instabilities of Growing Sheets" at PHASME 2016, Cargese, Corsica, August, 8–20.
- M. Pezzulla, G. P. Smith, P. Nardinocchi, and D. P. Holmes. "Geometry and Mechanics of Thin Growing Bilayers" at APS March Meeting 2016, Baltimore, Maryland, USA, March, 13–18.
- D. P. Holmes, M. Pezzulla, P. Nardinocchi, and S. A. Shillig. "Morphing and snapping of plates and shells via swelling" at APS March Meeting 2015, San Antonio, Texas, USA, March, 2–6.
- M. Pezzulla, S. A. Shillig, P. Nardinocchi, and D. P. Holmes. "Morphing of geometric composites via residual swelling" at 61st New England Complex Fluids Meeting, Harvard University, USA, December, 5.
- P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla and L. Teresi. "Anisotropic swelling of thin gel films" at NEW.Mech 2014, University of Massachusetts Amherst, USA, October, 18.
- P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla and L. Teresi. "Anisotropic swelling in fibrous materials" at the 17th U.S. National Congress on Theoretical and Applied Mechanics, Michigan State University, USA, June, 15–20.
- A. Lucantonio, P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla and L. Teresi. "Electromechanical model and motion control of soft bio-hybrid systems" at the INdAM Meeting "The Mathematics of Cells and Tissues", Cortona, Italy, September, 2–6.
- A. Lucantonio, P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla, V. Pugliese and L. Teresi. "Modeling Tools for Soft Robotics" at the Soft Robotic Conference, Ascona, Switzerland, July (Poster).
- Y. Cha, P.Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla and M. Porfiri. "Giant displacement in IPMC–based structures: a preliminary study" at the 6th ECCOMAS Thematic Conference on Smart Structures and Materials (SMART2013), Torino, Italy, June, 24–26.

Invited Seminars

2020 Towards Fluid-Shells Interactions. Aarhus University, Aarhus, Denmark, April.

- 2016 Geometry and Instabilities in Growing Shells. Sapienza Università di Roma, Rome, Italy, December.
- 2016 Geometry and Instabilities in Growing Shells. Physical Mathematics Seminar, MIT, Cambridge, MA, October
- Morphing of geometric composites. Form Finding Workshop, Roma Tre University, Rome, Italy, April.
- Morphing of Geometric Composites via Residual Swelling. Bertoldi Group Meeting, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA, December.

SUBMITTED PUBLICATIONS OR PUBLICATIONS IN PREPARATION

- M. Pezzulla, P. Leroy-Catalayud, and P. M. Reis. Fluid-Structure Interactions in Bristled Strips. *In preparation*
- 2020 T. G. Sano, M. Pezzulla, and P. M. Reis. A Reduced Theory for Magnetic Rods. In preparation
- 2020 M. Pezzulla, D. Yan, A. Abbasi, and P. M. Reis. A Reduced Theory for Magnetic Shells. In preparation
- D. Yan, M. Pezzulla, L. Cruveiller, and P. M. Reis Tuning the Buckling Strength of Magnetically-active Elastic Shells. *In preparation*
- M. Pezzulla, E. F. Strong, F. Gallaire, and P. M. Reis. Drag on Porous Flexible Strips at Low and Moderate Reynolds Numbers. *Submitted*
- D. P. Holmes, J.-H. Lee, H. S. Park, and M. Pezzulla. The nonlinear buckling behavior of a complete spherical shell under uniform external pressure and homogenous natural curvature. *Submitted*

Journals & Conference Proceedings

- * Papers with alphabetical ordering of authors in which I gave a *first author* contribution.
- D. Yan, M. Pezzulla, and P. M. Reis. Buckling of pressurized spherical shells containing a throughthickness defect. *J. Mech. Phys. Solids* 138, 103923 (2020)
- M. Pezzulla and P. M. Reis. A Weak Form Implementation of Nonlinear Axisymmetric Shell Equations with Examples. ASME. J. Appl. Mech. 86(12): 124502, (2019)
- E. F. Strong, M. Pezzulla, F. Gallaire, P. M. Reis, and L. Siconolfi. Hydrodynamic loading of perforated disks in creeping flows. *Phys. Rev. Fluids* 4, 084101, (2019)
- A. Lee, D. Yan, M. Pezzulla, D. P. Holmes, and P. M. Reis. Evolution of critical buckling conditions in imperfect bilayer shells through residual swelling. *Soft Matter* 15, 6134-6144, (2019)
- L. Stein-Montalvo, P. Costa, M. Pezzulla and D. P. Holmes. Buckling of Geometrically Confined Shells. *Soft Matter* 15, 1215-1222, (2019)
- X. Jiang, M. Pezzulla, S. Wei, T. K. Ghosh, and D. P. Holmes. Snapping of Bistable, Prestressed Cylindrical Shells. *Europhys. Lett.* 122, 64003, (2018)
- M. Pezzulla, N. Stoop, M. P. Steranka, A. J. Bade, and D. P. Holmes. Curvature-Induced Instabilities of Shells. *Phys. Rev. Lett.* 120, 048002, (2018)
- M. Pezzulla, N. Stoop, X. Jiang, and D. P. Holmes. Curvature-Driven Morphing of Non-Euclidean Shells. *Proc. R. Soc. A* 473(2201), 20170087, (2017)
- M. Pezzulla, G. P. Smith, P. Nardinocchi, and D. P. Holmes. Geometry and Mechanics of Thin Growing Bilayers. *Soft Matter* 12, 4435-4442, (2016)

- P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla, and L. Teresi. Steady and transient analysis of anisotropic swelling in fibered gels. J. Appl. Phys. 118, 244904, (2015)
- M. Pezzulla, S. A. Shillig, P. Nardinocchi, and D. P. Holmes. Morphing of geometric composites via residual swelling. *Soft Matter* 11, 5812-5820, (2015) [Inside Front Cover]
- *P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla, and L. Teresi, Mechanics of bio-hybrid systems. *Procedia IUTAM* 12, pp. 145-153, (2015)
- *P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla, and L. Teresi, Anisotropic swelling of thin gel sheets. *Soft Matter* 11, 1492-1499, (2015)
- A. Lucantonio, P. Nardinocchi, and M. Pezzulla. Swelling-induced and controlled curving in layered gel beams. *Proc. R. Soc. A* 470(2171), 20140467, (2014)
- *A. Lucantonio, P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla, and L. Teresi. Multiphysics of bio-hybrid systems: shape control and electro-induced motion. *Smart Mater. Struct.* 23(4), 045043, (2014)
- P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla, B.J. Akle, M. Guenther, and T. Wallmersperger. Actuation and buckling effects in IPMCs. *Proc. SPIE* 9056, (2014)
- Y. Cha, P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla, and M. Porfiri. Giant displacements in IPMC-based structures: a preliminary study. Adv. Mat. Res. 745, 119–128, (2013)
- *P.Nardinocchi and M. Pezzulla. Curled actuated shapes of ionic polymer metal composites. J. Appl. Phys. 113, 224906, (2013)
- *P. Nardinocchi, M. Pezzulla, and L. Placidi. Thermodynamically based multiphysic modeling of ionic polymer metal composites. J. Intel. Mat. Syst. Str. 22(16), 1887–1897, (2011)

Honors

| 2016 | PHASME 2016 Travel Grant, ICAM (USD 1K), | |
|-----------|---|--|
| 2014 | Research Project Grant <i>Giovani Ricercatori</i> , INdAM (€ 1.6K), "Corrugamento di travi bistrato di gel polimerico" | |
| 2014 | Research Project Young Investigator Grant, Sapienza University (\leqslant 2K), "Shaping of bio-hybrid systems: reduced models and numerical simulations" | |
| 2013-2015 | Graduate Research Fellowship, Italian Ministry of Education | |
| 2012 | ADISU M.Sc. degree award | |
| 2010 | ADISU B.Sc. degree award | |
| 2007-2012 | ADISU scholarship | |

TEACHING AND SERVICE

| 2019 | Preparation of the lectures on shells for the class on <i>Mechanics of Slender Structures</i> EPFL, Instructor: Prof. Pedro M. Reis |
|-----------|---|
| 2017 | Guest Lecture on the Buckling of Columns for the class on <i>Mechanics of Materials</i> Boston University, Instructor: Prof. Harold S. Park |
| 2015-2019 | Reviewer for Journal of Intelligent Materials Systems and Structures, Journal of Applied Mechanics, Proceedings of the Royal Society A, International Journal of Solids and Structures, Soft Matter |

Teaching Assistant for the class on *Mechanics of Solids and Structures* (Instructor: Prof. P. Nardinocchi)

2012–2015 Co–advisor for bachelor theses in Aerospace Engineering and master theses in Aeronautical Engineering (Advisor: Prof. P. Nardinocchi)

Mentoring

| MENTORING | |
|----------------------|---|
| Michele Curatolo | Ph.D. Student in Mechanical Engineering, Roma Tre University Adhesion and Swelling of an Elastica |
| Paul Costa | Master Student in Mechanical Engineering, École Polytechnique Curvature Buckling of Constrained Shells |
| Lucia Stein-Montalvo | Ph.D. Student in Mechanical Engineering, Boston University Theory and Numerical Simulations on Plates and Shells |
| Xin Jiang | Ph.D. Student in Mechanical Engineering, Boston University Theory and Numerical Simulations on Plates and Shells |
| Jay Shunter | Ph.D. Student in Mechanical Engineering, Boston University Differential Geometry and the Elastica |
| Mark Steranka | Undegraduate Student in Mechanical Engineering, Boston University Experiments on Spherical Snapping Bilayer Shells |
| Abdikhalaq Bade | Undegraduate Student in Mechanical Engineering, Boston University Experiments on Spherical Buckling Bilayer Shells and setup of a 3D scanner |
| Eric Fu | High School Student - RISE program Fabrication of Conical Bilayer Shells and Realization of an Experimental Setup for Image Processing |
| Marco Rossi | Master Student in Aeronautical Engineering, Sapienza - Università di Roma Numerical, Analytical and Experimental investigation on Ionic Polymer Metal Composites |
| Lorenzo Teofili | Master Student in Space Engineering, Sapienza - Università di Roma Motion Control Analysis Of a Bio-Hybrid Actuator |
| Andrea Pitzalis | Undergraduate Student in Aerospace Engineering, Sapienza - Università di Roma <i>Material Characteristics of IPMCs: Calibration Tests</i> |
| Francesco Saltari | Undergraduate Student in Aerospace Engineering, Sapienza - Università di Roma Bending Modes in IPMCs Induced by Non Homogeneous Differences in Voltage |
| Giulia Murzilli | Undergraduate Student in Aerospace Engineering, Sapienza - Università di Roma An Analytical Model for Bio-hybrid Beams |
| Virginia Notaro | Undergraduate Student in Aerospace Engineering, Sapienza - Università di Roma Nonlinear Analytical Modeling of Buckling in IPMCs |

Language & Programming Skills

- * Mother tongue: Italian. Fluent in English. Intermediate knowledge of French and Spanish.
- * Experience programming in C, Fortran, and Python.
- * Experience with mathematical software such as Matlab, Mathematica, LabView, LabVie
- \star Experience with FE software such as COMSOL Multiphysics, ADINA, Nastran.
- * Experience with Adobe Illustrator, Blender, MeshLab, Paraview and ImageJ.

References

- * Douglas P. Holmes, Boston University, Boston, USA (dpholmes@bu.edu)
- * Paola Nardinocchi, Sapienza Università di Roma, Roma, Italy (paola.nardinocchi@uniroma1.it)
- * Pedro M. Reis, *EPFL*, Lausanne, Switzerland (pedro.reis@epfl.ch)

L's.

April, 2020